Narrator: All right.
So, we've talked quite a bit about filters
in the context of our data model
and how filters can transmit through table relationships.
But now we're gonna talk
about filter context and how it impacts DAX measures.
So, remember the definition of a measure.
It's evaluated based on filter context, which means
that those measures recalculate whenever the fields
or filters around them change.
Consider this matrix view on the left-side of the screen.
If we pinpoint one cell of that matrix,
we can understand exactly what filter context
is being passed to that cell and therefore,
understand exactly how that measure is being calculated.
So for this example, highlighted cell,
we're calculating a measure called orders
and it's evaluating based on the following filter context.
The product name column
from the product table is equal to mountain tire tube
because that's the filter context that's passed
to the cell from the matrix row label, right?
And then it's calculating our total orders
based on that product context.
So, this is pretty intuitive on the surface.
This allows the measure,
this total orders measured to return our order quantity
for each product specifically
or whatever the matrix row and column label dictates.
So this could be years, it could be countries,
product categories, customer name, you know,
any other column or dimension that you could add in here.
So, again, pretty straightforward
but what might not be quite
as straightforward is the fact that total
or grand total values are not simply calculated by summing
or averaging or whatever the aggregation method is.
The values above, right?
They're calculated as their own unique measures.
So in this case, since we are calculating orders
for a specific product in the total row,
we're essentially taking that filter context
of the product name
and just ignoring it, right?
At a total row,
there is no specific or individual product filter context.
So it's a bit of a nuanced concept,
but it's a very important thing to understand.
And it's that each measure within a report behaves
like it's being calculated on its own island
and it calculates according
to its own unique filter context,
even totals and grand total rows and values.
So as a pro tip here, if you're struggling
to understand the filter context or trying
to understand the filter context impacting a visual,
you can click on the header icon to see a list of filters
and slicers, which are all part of that filter context
that's impacting the visual.
So here in this example, we can see
a customer metric selection, income level and year
are all affecting our donut chart visual.
As I was learning about filter context for the first time,
one of the most helpful things for me was working
through a number of different examples.
So, let's take a minute and we'll do that now.
So here, you've got a sample view of a dashboard.
This is actually a piece
of a dashboard that we're gonna be building
in the database section of this course.
And obviously, there's a ton
of different information here, right?
We've got cards and donut charts and line charts
with trends, and we've got matrix visuals and some slicers.
And there's just a whole bunch of stuff going on here.
And one thing to pay specific attention to
is this page level filter
and the filter pane that says year is 2021 or 2022.
Now we're gonna talk about what these filters mean
and how they work, but for now,
all you really need to know is that this filter applies
to every visual, every number,
everything that you see on this entire page.
This is a page level filter.
It impacts everything on the page.
So from here,
we can actually pinpoint individual measure values
to understand what filter context is being passed to them.
This first case in the top-left here,
we're evaluating a measure named revenue per customer.
And the filter context is that year equals 2021 or 2022.
Again, that's coming from our page level filter.
So with that filter context in mind,
the DAX calculation for revenue per customer evaluates
and spits out the result that we can see here.
In this case, we see that average revenue
per customer is $1,074.
Let's look at another example here.
So, now we're not looking
at an actual numerical value, right?
We're looking at a tool tip that's been generated as part
of a numerical value that's trended in a line chart, right?
So, this line chart is currently showing
the total customer's measure trended by day
but the tool tip is highlighting a specific day.
So, we're adding additional filter context
of September 26th, 2021,
just to generate the total customer value
within that tool tip.
So you might be thinking at this point, "Hey,
what happened to that year filter context?"
Well, it's still there, but in this case,
the more granular filter context of day wins out
to show total customers only for September 26th.
All right, so moving down to our donut chart,
we're evaluating total orders here, and again,
we've got that same 2021, 2022-year filter context.
The chart here is breaking down total orders by occupation.
So, in this particular highlighted cell
or segment of the donut chart, the second piece
of the filter context is that the occupation field
and the customer table equals skilled manual.
Moving over to the matrix visual,
here's an interesting one too, because in this case,
we're looking at a total row for a measure called revenue.
So, even though this value lives in a matrix
that's broken down by customer names, because this measure,
this little island cell needs to calculate the total,
we're basically calculating orders
in the absence of a specific customer filter.
Our filter context for this total is calendar year,
again, as 2021 or 2022.
But here, what we're actually doing is we're saying,
"I want you to return the total but filter
based on the top 100 customers
when we sort by total orders."
So, this total value is showing the total revenue
for our top 100 customers.
It's important to understand that even though
that total line doesn't have a customer-specific filter,
it is returning based on the filter
of the top 100 customers.
Up next here, we've got another example of a card visual
and this time we're showing total revenue.
But what's neat here is that we've added the top customer
by revenue filter context to return the revenue-specific
to that customer, right?
So for here, it's actually grabbing filter context
where the customer full name equals Mr. Maurice Shan, right?
Because that's in our top customers by revenue above.
And here, where we see Mr. Maurice Shan,
this is another card visual
but we're actually using the customer full-name
calculated column, and then applying filters to produce
a single name based on additional filter context.
So, we've got that same year page level filter
but we're adding onto that a filter
for our top one customer based on the total revenue.
And what's cool is you can actually verify this
from the matrix visual that Mr. Maurice Shan
is our top revenue driving customer.
So hopefully, these examples are helpful.
I imagine that you're thinking to yourself, you know,
it's all pretty straightforward, pretty intuitive,
but the thing is, it does get a bit more complicated
and a bit more interesting.
And to be honest, these views
on this page aren't static views.
This is an interactive dynamic dashboard
with a bunch of different visuals.
And what I mean by that is a user could drill
into different occupations within this donut chart, right?
So, if they were to drill into skilled manual,
that filter context is going to be added
to all of the other visuals that we've talked about.
It's gonna be added to all the visuals that we didn't talk
about that are on this page, right?
So every single measure, everything
on this page is going to have an updated filter context
based on that selection of skilled manual.
And now, let's say you wanted to look
at a specific income level based on the occupation type.
So then, if you were to drill into average income as well,
that's another piece of filter context
that is going to be added
to each one of these visuals around the page.
So, as you can probably tell,
it can get quite a bit more sophisticated
and much more complicated
and that's why it's really important
for us to really nail down these fundamentals
and understand exactly what's going on.
So, we're gonna talk through a number
of examples as we continue writing DAX functions.
And then this will really come into play in a number
of different ways later on in the course
when we actually start building visuals and reports.
So stay tuned, we've got some great stuff ahead.